It was just an ordinary Saturday.
كان مجرد يوم سبت عادي.
My dad was outside mowing the lawn,
كان والدي بالخارج يجز العشب،
my mom was upstairs folding laundry,
وأمي في الأعلى تطوي الملابس،
my sister was in her room doing homework
وشقيقتي تؤدي الواجب المنزلي في حجرتها
and I was in the basement playing video games.
وأنا في القبو ألعب بألعاب الفيديو.
And as I came upstairs to get something to drink,
وعندما صعدت للأعلى لأحضر شيئاً أشربه،
I looked out the window
نظرت خارج النافذة
and realized that there was something that I was supposed to be doing,
أدركت أن هناك شيئاً ما كان من المفترض أن أفعله
and this is what I saw.
وهذا ما شاهدته.
No, this wasn't my family's dinner on fire.
كلا، لم يكن هذا عشاء أسرتي على النار.
This was my science project.
كان هذا مشروعي العلمي.
Flames were pouring out,
كان اللهب يتطاير،
smoke was in the air
كان الدخان في الهواء.
and it looked like our wooden deck was about to catch fire.
ويبدوا أن السقف الخشبي لدينا كان على وشك أن تشتعل فيه النيران.
I immediately started yelling.
بدأت في الصراخ على الفور.
My mom was freaking out,
فقدت أمي صوابها،
my dad ran around to put out the fire
وركض والدي لإخماد النيران.
and of course my sister started recording a Snapchat video.
وكانت أختي بالطبع تسجل فيديو على (سناب شات)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This was just the beginning of my team's science project.
كانت هذه مجرد البداية للمشروع العلمي لفريقي.
My team is composed of me and three other students
يتكون الفريق مني أنا وثلاثة طلاب آخرين
who are here in the audience today.
متواجدين هنا اليوم بين المستمعين.
We competed in FIRST LEGO League
تنافسنا في فيرست ليجو ليغو
which is an international LEGO robotics competition for kids,
وهي مسابقة دولية لروبوتات ليجو للأطفال.
and in addition to a robotics game,
وبالإضافة إلى لعبة الروبوتات،
we also worked on a separate science project,
عملنا أيضاً على مشروع علمي منفصل،
and this was the project that we were working on.
وكان هذا هو المشروع الذي كنا نعمل عليه.
So the idea for this project all started
لذا بدأت فكرة هذا المشروع كلها
when a few months earlier,
قبل بضعة أشهر، عندما
a couple of my teammates took a trip to Central America
قام اثنان من زملائي بنزهة إلى أمريكا الوسطى
and saw beaches littered with Styrofoam,
وشاهدوا الشواطئ المغطاة بالستايروفوم
or expanded polystyrene foam.
أو رغوة البوليستيرين المطرّقة.
And when they came back and told us about it,
وعندما عادوا وأخبرونا عن ذلك،
we really started thinking about the ways in which we see Styrofoam every day.
بدأنا نفكر في الطرق التي نرى فيها الستايروفوم كل يوم.
Get a new flat-screen TV?
الحصول على شاشة تلفاز مسطحة جديدة؟
You end up with a block of Styrofoam bigger than the TV itself.
ينتهي بك الحال بكتلة من الستيروفوم أكبر من التلفاز نفسه.
Drink a cup of coffee?
شرب فنجان من القهوة؟
Well, those Styrofoam coffee cups are sure going to add up.
حسنا، أكواب القهوة المصنوعة من الستايروفوم بالتأكيد سوف تتراكم.
And where do all these items go after their one-time use?
وأين تذهب كل هذه العناصر بعد استخدامها لمرة واحدة؟
Since there aren't any good existing solutions for used Styrofoam,
وبما أنه لا توجد أي حلول جيدة لاستخدام الستايروفوم المستعمل،
almost all of them end up right in the landfill,
وينتهي بها المطاف كلها في مكب النفايات
or the oceans and beaches,
أو المحيطات والشواطئ،
taking over 500 years to degrade.
مع أكثر من 500 سنة لتتحلل.
And in fact, every year, the US alone
والواقع أن الولايات المتحدة وحدها
produces over two billion pounds of Styrofoam,
تنتج سنوياً أكثر من ملياري رطل من الستايروفوم،
filling up a staggering 25 percent of landfills.
وتشغل 25 في المائة من مدافن القمامة.
So why do we have these ghost accumulations of Styrofoam waste?
فلماذا لدينا هذه التراكمات الهائلة من نفايات الستايروفوم؟
Why can't we just recycle them like many plastics?
لماذا لا يمكننا إعادة تدويرها مثل العديد من البلاستيكات؟
Well, simply put, recycled polystyrene is too expensive
حسنا، البوليسترين المعاد تدويره مكلف للغاية،
and potentially contaminated,
وربما ملوث.
so there is very little market demand for Styrofoam that has to be recycled.
لذلك هناك القليل جداً من الطلب في السوق على الستايروفوم المعاد تدويره.
And as a result, Styrofoam is considered a nonrenewable material,
ونتيجة لذلك، يعتبر الستايروفوم مادة غير قابلة للتجديد،
because it is neither feasible nor viable to recycle polystyrene.
لأنه ليس من المجدي إعادة تدوير البوليسترين.
And in fact, many cities across the US
والعديد من المدن في جميع أنحاء الولايات المتحدة
have even passed ordinances
قد مررت تشريعات
that simply ban the production of many products containing polystyrene,
والتي تحظر إنتاج العديد من المنتبجات التي تحتوي على البوليسترين،
which includes disposable utensils,
والتي تشمل الأواني التي تستعمل لمرة واحدة
packing peanuts, takeout containers
والفول السوداني المُعبأ وعبوات الأطعمة الجاهزة.
and even plastic beach toys,
وحتى ألعاب الشاطئ البلاستيكية.
all products that are very useful in today's society.
وجميع المنتجات المفيدة جداً في المجتمع اليوم.
And now France has become the first country
والآن أصبحت فرنسا أول بلد
to completely ban all plastic utensils,
يحظر تماماً جميع الأواني البلاستيكية
cups and plates.
والأكواب والأطباق.
But what if we could keep using Styrofoam
لكن ماذا لو تمكنا من استخدام الستايروفوم
and keep benefiting from its cheap, lightweight, insulating
والحفاظ على الاستفادة من رخصها وخفة وزنها وقدرتها على العزل
and excellent packing ability,
وقابليتها الجيدة للتعبئة،
while not having to suffer from the repercussions
بدون أن نعاني من تداعيات
of having to dispose of it?
الاضطرار إلى التخلص منه؟
What if we could turn it into something else that's actually useful?
ماذا لو تمكنا من تحويله إلى شيء آخر مفيد فعلاً؟
What if we could make the impossible possible?
ماذا لو تمكنا من جعل المستحيل ممكنا؟
My team hypothesized that we could use the carbon that's already in Styrofoam
افترض فريقي أننا يمكن أن نستخدم الكربون الموجود بالفعل في الستايروفوم
to create activated carbon,
لتكوين الكربون المنشط،
which is used in almost every water filter today.
المستخدم في كل مرشحات المياه تقريباً اليوم.
And activated carbon works by using very small micropores
ويعمل الكربون المنشط باستخدام المسامات الدقيقة للغاية
to filter out contaminants from water or even air.
لتصفية الملوثات من الماء أو حتى الهواء.
So we started out by doing a variety of heating tests,
بدأنا من خلال القيام بمجموعة متنوعة من اختبارات التدفئة،
and unfortunately, we had many failures.
وللأسف، فشلنا كثيراً.
Literally, nothing worked.
حرفياً، لم ينجح أي شئ.
Besides my dad's grill catching on fire,
إلى جانب اشتعال النيران بشواية أبي،
most of our samples vaporized into nothing,
ومعظم العينات لدينا تبخرت هباء،
or exploded inside expensive furnaces,
أو انفجرت داخل أفران باهظة الثمن،
leaving a horribly sticky mess.
وتركت فوضى لزجة فظيعة.
In fact, we were so saddened by our failures that we almost gave up.
والواقع أننا شعرنا بالحزن الشديد بسبب إخفاقاتنا التي جعلتنا نستسلم.
So why did we keep trying
فلماذا ظللنا نحاول
when all the adults said it was impossible?
عندما قال جميع البالغين أنه من المستحيل؟
Well, maybe it's because we're kids. We don't know any better.
حسناً، ربما لأننا أطفال. نحن لا نفقه أي شئ.
But the truth is, we kept trying because we thought it was still possible.
لكن الحقيقة هي أننا ظلنا نحاول لأننا نظن أنه لا يزال ممكناً.
We knew that if we were successful,
كنا نعلم أنه إذا كنا ناجحين،
we would be helping the environment and making the world a better place.
فإننا سوف نساعد البيئة ونجعل العالم مكاناً أفضل.
So we kept trying
استمرينا في المحاولة
and failing
والفشل
and trying
والمحاولة
We were so ready to give up.
وكنا على استعداد للتخلي عن ذلك.
But then it happened.
ولكن حدث بعد ذلك.
With the right temperatures, times and chemicals,
مع درجات الحرارة المناسبة والتوقيتات والمواد الكيميائية،
we finally got that successful test result
وأخيراً حصلنا على نتيجة الاختبار الناجحة
showing us that we had created activated carbon from Styrofoam waste.
تبين لنا أننا قد أخرجنا الكربون المنشط من نفايات الستايروفوم.
And at that moment, the thing that had been impossible
وفي تلك اللحظة، الشيء الذي كان مستحيلاً
all of a sudden wasn't.
فجأة لم يكن كذلك.
It showed us that although we had many failures at the beginning,
وأظهر لنا أنه على الرغم من الإخفاقات العديدة في البداية،
we were able to persevere through them to get the test results that we wanted.
كنا قادرين على المثابرة خلالها للحصول على نتائج الاختبار التي أردناها.
And moreover, not only were we able to create activated carbon
وعلاوة على ذلك، لم نستطع فقط إنتاج الكربون المنشط
for purifying water,
لتنقية المياه،
but we were also able to reduce Styrofoam waste,
لكن استطعنا أيضاً التقليل من نفايات الستايروفوم،
solving two global problems with just one solution.
حل اثنتين من المشاكل العالمية بحل واحد فقط.
So from then on, we were inspired to take our project further,
منذ ذلك الحين، أصبحنا محفزين لتطوير مشروعنا،
performing more tests to make it more effective
وإجراء المزيد من الاختبارات لجعله أكثر فعالية
and testing it in real world situations.
واختباره في ظروف واقعية.
We then proceeded to receive funding
ثم شرعنا في الحصول على التمويل
from the NSTA's eCYBERMISSION STEM-in-Action program
من برنامج إسيبرميسيون التابع لوكالة الامن القومي
sponsored by the US Army,
برعاية الجيش الأمريكي،
as well as FIRST Global Innovation Awards
وكذلك جوائز فيرست العالمية للابتكار
sponsored by XPRIZE.
برعاية XPRIZE
And we were also honored
كما تم تكريمنا
with the Scientific American Innovator Award
بجائزة سسينتيفيك أمريكان إنوفاتور
from Google Science Fair.
من معرض غوغل للعلوم.
And using these funds, we plan to file a full patent on our process
وباستخدام هذه الأموال، فإننا نخطط لتقديم براءة اختراع كاملة للمشروع
and to continue to work on our project.
ومواصلة العمل على مشروعنا.
So yes, although we started with catching my dad's grill on fire
نعم، على الرغم من أننا بدأنا بشواية أبي تشتعل
and failing so many times that we almost quit,
وفشل عدة مرات، فقد كدنا ننتهي تقريباً،
it was well worth it when we look back at it now.
كان ذلك يستحق إذا نظرنا الآن إلى الوراء.
We took a problem that many people said was impossible
لقد واجهنا مشكلة قال كثير من الناس إنها مستحيلة،
and we made it possible,
وجعلناها ممكنة،
and we persevered when it looked like nothing that we did would work.
وناضلنا عندما بدا وكأن لا شيئ مما فعلناه سيعمل.
We learned that you can't have success
علمنا أنه لا يمكن أن يكون النجاح
without a little,
دون القليل،
or a lot, of failure.
أو الكثير من الفشل.
So in the future, don't be afraid if your grill goes up in flames,
لذلك في المستقبل، لا تخافوا إذا كانت شوايتكم تشتعل فيها النيران،
because you never know when your idea might just catch fire.
لأنك لا تعرف متى تشتعل فكرتك فحسب.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)